<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three tracts written by Robert Boyle.</title>
            <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26552</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09498676</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09498676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43313</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1325:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three tracts written by Robert Boyle.</title>
                  <author>Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 42, 21, 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.H. for Ric. Davis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Each of the treatises has special t.p. and separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Of the temperature of the subterraneall regions--Of the temperature of the submarine regions--Of the bottom of the sea.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Temperature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Deep-sea temperature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heat --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="docket_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:1"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">R</hi> Boyles HISTORY OF PARTICULAR QUALITIES.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>THREE TRACTS WRITTEN By the Honourable ROBERT BOYLE.</p>
            <p>Of the
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Temperature of the Subterraneall Regions.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Temperature of the Submarine Regions.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bottom of the Sea.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>W.H.</hi> for <hi>Ric. Davis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1671.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THe two following Tracts were deſign'd to have been accompanied by three or four O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whereof the Firſt, Treated about the Temperature of the Regions of the Air, as to Heat and Cold, and had been premiſed to the Two that now come forth, had it not been judged more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to reſerve them to accompany ſome other Papers concerning the Air. To the following Tract about the Submarine Regions, it is thought fit to adjoyne ſome Relations about the Bottom of the Sea, to which was to have been added ſome Obſervations, concerning the Saltneſs of the Sea; but in that Treatiſe, ſome Blanks having been left for Particulars, which the Author could not ſeaſonably find among his Loos Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to fill them up with, theſe that now appear, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no dependence on them, it was not thought ſit they ſhould ſtay any longer for them.</p>
            <p>But about theſe ſeverall Tracts, this Generall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement is to be here given, That being Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Pieces, conſiſting <hi>chiefly,</hi> (though not only,) of ſuch Particulars, as the Author muſt owe to the Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Others, he would not ſtake his Reputation for the Truth of every one of them; contenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to have performed what can be reaſonably expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of him; which is, that he ſhould carefully make his Inquiries from credible Perſons, who for the moſt part, deliver their Anſwer upon their own knowledge, and that he ſhould faithfully ſet down the accounts he procured from ſuch Relators.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:3"/>
            <head>Of the TEMPERATURE Of the SUBTERRANEAL REGIONS, As to <hi>HEAT</hi> and <hi>COLD.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:43313:4"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43313:4"/>
               <head>OF THE TEMPERATURE, Of the SUBTERRANEALL REGIONS. <hi>As to Heat and Cold.</hi> CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>IF when I uſed to viſit mines, I had thought of writing on the ſubject I am now about to treat of, and had deſign'd to ſatisfie my ſelfe about the Temperature of the Subterraneall Air, as much as I did about the other Subjects I was then concern'd to be inform'd of, I think I ſhould have enabled my ſelfe to deliver much more upon my own obſervation, then I ſhall now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to doe. But though for the reaſon newly intimated, and becauſe of my being particularly ſubject to be offended by any thing that hinders a full freedom of Reſpiration, I was not ſolicitous to goe down into the deep mines; yet after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving discourſ'd of the Temperature of the Air a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Ground, I preſume it may not be impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or unwellcome to ſay ſomething of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the Subterraneall Regions and of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43313:5"/>the Air reaching thither. For deep mines being places which very few have had the opportunity, and fewer have had the curioſity to viſit, and of which I have ſcarce found any thing at all obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable by Claſſick Authors, and by other writers, but very little, eſpecially that I think probable enough to make uſe of, I preſume it will not be unacceptable to you, if of Regions ſo little fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, and leſs known, I report what I have been able to learn (by diligent enquiry purpoſely made) from the credible Relations of ſeverall Eye-witneſſes differing in nation, and for the moſt part unacquainted with each other.</p>
               <p>Though I do not think it abſurd to ſuſpect that in ſome places of the Earth, the peculiar conſtitution of the Soil, and other circumſtances, may make it reaſonable to aſſign thoſe places fewer or more Regions then three; yet ſpeaking in the Generall, the Ternary number ſeems not inconvenient to be aſſigned to the Subterraneall Regions, not ſo much upon the ſcore of the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, that by this Diviſion will be eſtabliſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Regions of the Earth and of the Air, as becauſe there ſeems to be a reaſon of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion included in the Diviſion itſelfe. And indeed Experience appears to favour it in the Subterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall Cavity, that I have hitherto been able to procure an account of, from any Ocular witneſs, and (very few excepted) one of the deepeſt that we yet know of, in the world. And ſince it has been received for a Rule among Philoſophers,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43313:5"/>that which is perfecteſt or compleateſt in its kind, ought to be the Standard whereby the reſt are to be meaſured, or eſtimated, I ſhall begin the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part of this Eſſay by a Relation that I obtained from a Chymiſt, that had purpoſely travelled into Hungary, and other places to viſit the mines thoſe parts are juſtly famous for, and who bringing me the honour of a Complement from a Prince, to whom he belonged gave me the opportunity of asking him divers Queſtions, his Anſwers whereunto (which I preſently after put into writing,) afforded me the enſuing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>THat very near the Orifice of the Groove, he felt the Air yet warm; but afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending towards the lower parts of the Groove, he felt it cold, till he came to ſuch a depth, as he had ſcarce attained by a quarter of an hours deſcent, and that the Cold he felt during this time ſeem'd to him conſiderable, eſpecially when in deſcending he had reached to a good depth.</p>
               <p>That after he had paſſed that Cold Region, he began by degrees to come into a warmer one which increaſed in heat, as he went deeper and deeper. So that in the deeper veins he found the Workmen digging with only a ſlight garment over them; and the Subterraneal heat was much
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43313:6"/>greater, then that of the free Air on the top of the Groove, though it were then <hi>Summer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[What is here mention'd of a cold region in the Earth, has been ſince confirmed to me by an ingenious Phyſitian, upon an obſervation made in another Hungarian mine (near a Town whoſe name I remember not) that was not of Gold, but Copper; and of much leſſer deepneſſe then that newly ſpoken of. For this Relator anſwer'd me that in going down, he felt a conſiderable degree of Cold. And when I ask'd whether he found the like in his Return upwards, he told me, he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervd it then too. And when I further inquired after the extent of this cold Region, he replyed, that not expecting to be ask'd about ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, he had not taken particular notice of them: but thus much Information my Queſtions procur'd me, that he began to feel the above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd coldneſſe when he could receive no more light at all by the mouth of the Groove, and that this cold Region laſted till he came ſomewhat near the bottom, which was eſtimated to be about an 100 fathom or more diſtant (in a ſtrait Line) from the Top.]</p>
               <p>This Relation agrees well enough for the main, with that ſhort, but conſiderable one of <hi>Morinus,</hi> (which I elſewhere cite) who above forty five years agoe, viſited the deep Hungarian-mines in the month of July, and takes notice, that when he came down to the burrows, as he calls them, he did not find any heat, as at the mouth of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43313:6"/>Well; but the beginning of a very Cold, as well as conſiderably thick Region: though I eaſily beleive him, when he confeſſes, that he felt it much the Colder, becauſe he had left of his own Clothes, and put on the ſlight Garments uſed there by the Diggers. He further informs his Reader, that when they had deſcended about 80 fathoms beneath the ſurface of the Earth, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to feel a breath of an almoſt luke-warm air; which warmth increaſed upon him, as he deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded lower, pleaſing him not a little, becauſe it freed him from the troubleſome ſcents of his former coldneſſe. Adding that the Overſeer of the mine who conducted him, affirmed to him, as alſo the Officers of other Hungarian mines un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animouſly did, that in all their mines, at leaſt all the deep ones, after a thick tract of Cold Earth, there ſucceeds a Lower Region, that is alwaies hot. And that after they arriv'd at ſuch a depth, they felt not any more Cold, but alwaies Heat, how deep ſoever they digg. And to add upon the by, though this Learned Man lay much weight upon <hi>Antiperiſtaſis;</hi> yet in the next page to thoſe that contain what I have been juſt now relating, he either very candidly or inconſiderately takes notice, that they inform'd him, that their mines, whether more or leſſe deep, they obſerved that at ſome times in the year, a ſomewhat intenſer heat was felt, and the two Times that he expreſly names, are thoſe oppoſitely qualified Seaſons of <hi>Summer</hi> and <hi>Winter.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43313:7"/>
               <p>Having laid down theſe generall narratives, I now proceed to conſider the Earths Regions in particular, about which the Summe of what I yet have to propound, may be conveniently enough compriz'd in the 4 following Propoſitions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Propoſition the 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Firſt Region of the Earth is very variable, both as to Bounds, and as to Temperature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The former part of this obſervation will not be difficult to prove, ſince 'twill be eaſily granted, that the manifeſt operation of the <hi>Sun-Beams</hi> is <hi>(caeteris paribus)</hi> greater, and reaches further in hot Climates then in Cold ones; in the midſt of <hi>Summer,</hi> then in the depth of <hi>Winter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Second part of the Obſervation may be proved by the ſame Arguments as the Firſt; to which may be added, as to ſome places, the Solidity or porousneſs of the Earth, as alſo the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſome Salts, Marchaſites, and other Bodies contained in it, which by their natural Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature may diſpoſe the Soil to Coldneſs or Heat. As I ſhall have occaſion to ſhew, when I come to ſpeak of the ſecond Region.</p>
               <p>In the mean time I have this to obſerve fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That in this Firſt Region, the Air is uſually more temperate, as to Cold and Heat, then that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43313:7"/>above the ſurface of the Earth, and that this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is not wont to be conſiderably deep: Both parts of which Obſervation are capable of being made good by the ſame Reaſons, and therefore I ſhall endeavour to prove them jointly.</p>
               <p>That in the uppermoſt Region of the Earth, it ſhould be leſs cold then above the ſurface, ſeems reaſonable to be allowed upon this Conſideration, That the <hi>Subterraneall Cavities</hi> of the Earth are ſheltered by the thickneſs of the ſides, from the direct action of the Sun-Beams, the Winds, &amp;c. and is alſo kept from an immediate, or at leaſt from ſo full a contact of the externall Air, when that is vehemently, either heated or refri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerated.</p>
               <p>And firſt as to the heat of the Sun, that That does much leſs powerfully affect ſuch places as are ſheltered from its action by ſolid Bodies, may appear by the Conſervatories of Ice and Snow, wherein frozen water is kept in that State during all the Heat of <hi>Summer,</hi> and that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Cavities that are at no conſiderable depth beneath the Superficies of the Earth. Nay I remember that having had occaſion, (for the perfecting of ſome Concluſions I was trying) to keep Ice many weeks after the froſty Weather was gone, and a milder Seaſon was come in, I was able to doe it, (contrary to the expectation of ſome Curious men,) without either digging to a notable depth in the ground, or building any ſubſtantiall <hi>Structure</hi> over the Cavity. For wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43313:8"/>conveniencies, I contented my ſelfe (though 'twere in a champain place) with a pit ſomewhat broad at the bottom, of about four foot deep or leſſe, whoſe mouth was ſhelter'd only by a little low thatch'd hovell, that was wide open to the <hi>North,</hi> and only skreen'd the mouth or vent of the little pit from the direct Beams of the Sun. And though I will not deny, that in deep Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatories of Snow, the naturall Coldneſſe of the Earth, eſpecially in ſome places, may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the effect; yet I remember, that diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing once with a Traveller and Schollar that was born in hot Countries, of a conjecture of mine that in an arch'd building, whoſe walls were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently thick, and whoſe Air were carefully kept from all avoidable intercourſe with the externall Air, one may without digging ſo much as a mans depth into the Ground, make a ſufficient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatory for Ice in very open and unſhelter'd places, and even ſuch as <hi>Salisbury plain</hi> it ſelfe; diſcourſing (as I began to ſay) with this Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler about this Conjecture, he told me, that at a place he nam'd to me, in the Southern part of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe heat ſeem'd to me to exceed that of divers parts of <hi>Italy,</hi> ſome Curious perſons that were reſolv'd at any rate, to have Ice in <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> though the <hi>Soil</hi> were ſuch, that they could not dig 4 foot without meeting with water, were yet able to make uſe of Conſervatories by covering the Brick-Building they made over their pits, with <hi>Clay</hi> and <hi>Sand</hi> to a very conſiderable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43313:8"/>thickneſſe, and taking care that the only place that ſhould permit acceſſe to the outward Air, ſhould be a ſmall Northern Door to go in and out at, fitted to ſhut exactly cloſe, and fenc'd with a little porch furniſhed with another Door. And by this means he affirms theſe Gentlemen to reſerve the included Ice not only all the <hi>Summer</hi> long, but ſometimes for two or three years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the heat of that Region making many of their Winters too mild to recruit them with Ice.</p>
               <p>To all theſe things I ſhall add, that even where the intercourſe is not quite debarr'd, but left free enough betwixt the Subterraneall and the ſuperior Air, the operation of the Sun-Beams may be very much leſſe in a Cavity though but ſhallow, beneath the Surface of the Ground then above it. For beſides that Tryalls have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd me, that Liquors that differ in little elſe then in conſiſtence, will not ſo eaſily pervade each other, as a man would ſurmiſe; unleſſe ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall motion haſten their intimate mingling with one another. I remember that one morning pretty late, having had the Curioſity to deſcend into a pit where they were digging out Iron Oar; though this Cavity had no very narrow Orifice, and was dugg directly downwards, and exceeded not ten or twelve foot in depth: yet I found not the heat at all troubleſome whilſt I ſtaid there, Though the pit were in an open feild unſhaded by Trees, and though the Air abroad were much
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43313:9"/>heated at that time of the year, which was in that ſeaſon (or at leaſt very near it) that is wont to be call'd the Dogg-Daies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. <hi>IIII.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd as we have ſhewn, that the Subterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal Air, even in the firſt Region is uſually much leſs heated, then the <hi>Superterreſtriall Air;</hi> ſo we may alſo eaſily obſerve, that That Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Air is <hi>(Caeteris paribus)</hi> wont to be much leſs refrigerated by the grand Efficients of intenſe Cold, then the <hi>Superior Air.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will not urge on this occaſion what I have obſerved by a ſurer way, then for ought I know has been before practiſed, about the ſmoaking of ſome <hi>Springs</hi> in <hi>Froſty Weather;</hi> becauſe I doe not know but that thoſe <hi>Springs</hi> may have come from, or paſſed a good way through, ſome place very deep beneath the Surface of the directly incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ground, and perhaps from a Soil peculiarly fitted to warm them: whence the water may have deriv'd a warmth conſiderable enough not to be quite loſt, till it began to ſpring out of the ground, where it needed only not to be quite Cold to appear to ſmoke; the intenſe Coldneſs of the Air making thoſe exhalations viſible in <hi>Froſty Weather,</hi> which would not be ſo in mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: As is evident in a mans Breath, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears like a ſmoak in <hi>ſuch weather,</hi> though it be not viſible in <hi>Summer.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43313:9"/>
               <p>That therefore, which I ſhall propoſe in favour of our obſervation, is firſt taken from the nature of the thing, which may perſwade us, that the <hi>Subterraneall Air</hi> being though comparatively cool, yet indeed moderately warm in <hi>Summer,</hi> ought not to be affected with Winters Cold, ſo much as that contiguous to the <hi>Surface</hi> of the Earth, from whoſe immediate Contact, it is by a thick arch of Earth (if I may ſo call it) defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and that the Cold reigns moſt in the free Air; and the <hi>Superficiall</hi> parts of the Terreſtriall Globe, may appear by Waters beginning to freeze at the Top, not at the Bottom. To which Reaſon from the nature of the thing, I ſhall add only this from experience, that we ſee that in Cellars that are arch'd and carefully kept cloſe from the Communication of the outward Air, Beer, and other Liquors may be kept from free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing in froſty, and ſnowy Weather. As I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in a cellar that was but ſhallow, but well arch'd in a <hi>Winter</hi> that was ſharp to a wonder, and froze ſtronger Liquors then Beer in another Cellar very near it, that differed not much from it in depth, but had not ſo thick and ſolid a roof. And that not only here in <hi>England,</hi> where the Cold is leſs violent, but even in <hi>Ruſsia</hi> it ſelfe, where it is wont to be ſo extream, it reaches not near ſo deep as one would think, I learn'd by Inquiry purpoſely made of an ingenious Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an that lived at <hi>Moſco,</hi> who anſwered me, that others and he himſelfe, did in that City keep all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43313:10"/>the Winter long, not only their Wine but their Beer from freezing in Cellars that were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 12 or 14 foot deep, but well cover'd above, and carefully Lin'd with plankes of Firr, without any entrance, but a ſmall trap-Door (commonly at the top,) which was fitted ſo exactly to the Orifice it was to cloſe, as to exclude (as much as was poſſible) all communication between the internall and externall Air, that the latter might not affect the former with it's Coldneſſe.</p>
               <p>I have indeed ſuſpected that in ſome Cellars, the comparative warmth we find there, may be partly due to Subterraneall Exhalations that are pent up in them: and perhaps too in ſome meaſure from the Steams of the fermenting, or fermented Liquors lodg'd in thoſe places. And I was ſomewhat confirmed in this Suſpition, by an Information my Inquiries obtained from the newly mentioned Doctor, who told me upon his own obſervation, that in one of the Cellars he made uſe of at <hi>Moſco,</hi> having occaſion to open the above mentioned trap-door, after the Cellar had for a good while been kept very cloſe ſhut, there came out at the vent that was thereby given, a copious Steam in the forme of ſmoak, which to them, who had their Bodies affected with the externall Air, was very ſenſibly warm, and was almoſt unfit for Reſpiration. Which Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance increaſed my ſuſpition that there might be among theſe ſteames, ſome of the nature of thoſe,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43313:10"/>that have been obſerved to come from fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Liquors, eſpecially Wine, and ſo abound in ſome Cellars, as almoſt to ſtiffle thoſe that ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured into thoſe Vaults, And to kill ſome of them outright. Which effects the long abode of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneall <hi>Steams</hi> in ſtagnating Air, even in many places, where no metalline Oars at all, not other noxious mineralls have been found, has enabled that Air to produce. Of which divers ſad Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have been given within leſſe then a mile of this place, upon mens firſt going down into pitts or Wells, that had not in a long time been open'd or made uſe of: (but this is here mentioned only upon the By) nor have we any neceſſity to fly to <hi>Subterraneall Exhalations,</hi> for the Comparative warmth that good Cellars in generall afford in froſty weather; ſince that <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for, by the reaſon formerly given, That the cloſeneſſe of the Cavity, and the thickneſſe of the ſides and Roofe, keep it from being vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with the Cold of the Ambient Air.</p>
               <p>I know 'tis pretended that the warmth we ſpeak of, proceeds from an <hi>Antiperiſtaſis,</hi> but not now to engage in a controverſy that would take up too much time, it may here ſuffice to repreſent, that in our caſe there appears no neceſſity of recurring to it, the <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> being ſolvable by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion newly cited, which may be confirmed by this Experiment, that in the Vaulted Cellar above mention'd, wherein Beer was kept from freezing,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43313:11"/>in an almoſt prodigiouſly ſharp Winter, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Air, though ſenſibly warm, to thoſe that came out of the free Air, had not ſo intended its native heat, as the Aſſertors of <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iperiſtaſis</hi> would have expected; being Colder then the free Air commonly is in that place, not only in the heat of <hi>Summer,</hi> but in other ſeaſons, when the weather is Temperate; As I was aſſur'd by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring my own obſervations made at other times, with the account brought me by a skillfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whom I employ'd into that Cellar at late hours, in one or two of the ſharpeſt nights of the forementioned cruell winter with the ſame excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſeal'd weather-glaſs that I had long kept ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended within a ſtones caſt of that place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>HAving ſaid thus much about the Earths up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt Region, I now proceed to that which lies next beneath it; whoſe Temperature I cannot ſo conveniently give an account of, in leſs then two Propoſitions, whereof the Firſt is this;</p>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition the firſt.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Second Region of the Earth ſeems to be for the moſt part cold in compariſon of the other two.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This propoſition may be confirmed partly by Reaſon, and partly by experience.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43313:11"/>
                  <p>And firſt it ſeems conſonant to Reaſon, that ſince the Earth is naturally a Bodie conſiſting of groſs and heavy parts, that are <hi>uſually</hi> much leſſe agitated, then thoſe of our Organs of Feeling, it ſhould as to ſenſe be cold; and that therefore that quality may be juſtly aſcribed to it, in that Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on where by vertue of its ſituation, it is kept from being conſiderably affected, either by the heat of the Superior Air, or by that of the deep parts of the Earth: which upper, and lower heat are the two Agents, that ſeem of all others the moſt likely to put its parts into an unuſuall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thereby change its naturall Temper.</p>
                  <p>That our propoſition is alſo confirmable by Experience, may be gathered from the Relations ſet down in the former part of this diſcourſe,</p>
                  <p>And here it will be proper to take notice of the Advertiſement intimated in the cloſe of our above delivered propoſition, That this Coldneſſe aſcrib'd to the ſecond Region of the Earth, is to be underſtood comparatively to the other two. For otherwiſe that even this Earth is not (as many na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalliſts would have it) the <hi>Summum Frigidum</hi> I gather from this, That I could never hear of any Ice met with there, at any time of the year though <hi>Snow or Hail</hi> may be produced in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Region at differing, and ſometimes quite op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite ſeaſons of the year; nay, I have not found by the Anſwers that were made me by thoſe that have deſcended far enough into this Region, that they found the cold any where very great, or that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43313:12"/>in ſome places they have found it at all conſidera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. As we ſhall ſee in the explication of the next propoſition. I know not whether it will much ſtrengthen what has been ſaid, if I add, that I learned by inquiry of ſuch perſons as I lately men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that at the mouth of deep Grooves, in mines, the ſteams that aſcend, do often feel warm; though the outward Air where the Obſervation is made, be affected with the heat of <hi>Summer.</hi> But <hi>though</hi> this <hi>probably</hi> argue, that if the middle Region of the Earth, through which theſe Steams muſt aſcend, were very intenſely cold, they would be ſo refrigerated in their paſſage, as to feel ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cold then hot at their appearing above ground, eſpecially in Summer: yet I ſhall not lay much weight (for ſome may perhaps be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it) upon this Argument; becauſe I have not yet tryed, how far a warm Steam may be alter'd in its paſſage, thorow a Cold Conduit: not to mention that in the Earth, the paſſage by being directly upwards may be much the nimblier tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <p>THe ſecond propoſition relating to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the ſecond Region of the Earth, may be delivered in theſe Terms.</p>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition the 3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In ſeverall places, which by reaſon of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43313:12"/>from the ſurface of the Earth, one would refer to the middle Region of it, The Temperature of the Air is very differing at the ſame times of the year</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I choſe to expreſs my ſelfe thus, to prevent ſome ambiguities and objections which I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw, that ſhorter, but leſs dear and full expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, might give occaſion to.</p>
                  <p>In the proofe of our propoſition, both Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Reaſon may diſtinctly be employed. And to begin with experience,</p>
                  <p>Whereas in the above recited deſcent into the <hi>Hungarian-Mines,</hi> there was obſerved a notably Cold Region of a conſiderable thickneſs, I have purpoſely procured accounts from divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have here in <hi>England</hi> had occaſion, ſome of them frequently to deſcend into deep pits or Grooves of differing mineralls, without finding by the narratives they made me, that they took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of any notably cold part that they paſſed thorow; unleſs I particularly asked a queſtion about ſuch a thing. But for ought I could gather from their Spontaneous Relations, they felt in <hi>Summer-time</hi> a remiſſion of the heat of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Air, aſſoon as ever they began to deſcend; which warmth did not ſo far decreaſe, as to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in any notable Coldneſs, before they came into a deeper part of the Earth, where they are never troubled with that quality. And ſome of theſe Relations I had from profeſſed Miners, and was curious that the Relations I procured ſhoud
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43313:13"/>be of <hi>Subterraneall parts</hi> ſeated in very differing parts of <hi>England,</hi> as well as of places not all, or moſt of them having Veins of one and the ſame minerall. And I learned by particlar inquiry from a practicall Mathematician that was often employed about Lead-mines that at ſuch depths as, (according to <hi>Morinus</hi>) the ſecond Region of the Earth reaches to, he himſelfe obſerved it to be ſenſibly warm at all ſeaſons of the year (for about that Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance I was peculiarly ſolicitous to be ſatisfied.)</p>
                  <p>Nor is it unconſonant to Reaſon, that the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Region of the Earth, in the ſenſe meant in the propoſition, ſhould not be of the ſame tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature in all places; not only becauſe of the differences, which the Climate may produce, by reaſon of its being very much hotter, or very much colder in one place then in another: but from the peculiar conſtitution of the <hi>Soil;</hi> to the Conſideration whereof I ſhall here confine my ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Now this Temperament of the Soil it ſelfe may be divertified, not only by its greater or leſſer compactneſſe (upon which account ſome <hi>Soils</hi> are Rocky or ſtony and others Light and ſpongy) but from the nature of the ſprings or Subterraneous Liquors, that may abound in it, or ſtrain through it into the Groove or pit, we ſuppoſe the Obſerver to be in; and that eſpecially by the mineralls, particularly Salts, and Marcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites that grow near the ſides of the Well, or are brought thither by the waters.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43313:13"/>
                  <p>To illuſtrate this, give me leave to conſider, that nature dos not regulate her ſelfe under ground by our imaginary Diviſions: but, without taking notice of them, produces marchaſites, Salts, and other mineralls, moſt frequently (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) in what we call the lower Region of the Earth; but yet ſometimes to, in our upper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and oftentimes in our middlemoſt Region. Let us then ſuppoſe, that in ſome places of this laſt nam'd Region, there be a mine of that Earth that naturally abounds with embryonated nitre, or with ſome other ſalt that is apt, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſſolv'd or moiſtened with water, (a thing very familiarly to be met within in mines; to ſend out a refrigerating Effluvium, or by its contact to cool the Air. Let us alſo ſuppoſe that by the ſides of another Well of the ſame depth, there are ſtore of unripe mineralls that are in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of generation, or rather a great quantity of marchaſiticall Earth, if I may ſo call it, that is ſuch a ſubſtance, as I have met with, in more then one place, copiouſly impregnated and as it were blended with mineralls of a marchaſiticall nature; and yet of ſo open and looſe a Texture, as not only water would in a few hours, but Air alſo would in not very many, evidently worke upon it. And ſince during the time that marchaſites are ſlowly diſſolving, it has been obſerved accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what we have elſwhere delivered
<note n="*" place="margin">The Tract here pointed at is a Diſcourſe of Subterraneall Fires and Heats.</note> that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43313:14"/>many of them will conceive a very conſiderable degree of heat, will it not be very probable, that the Temperature of the Earth in the place that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds with theſe Marchaſiticall mineralls will be very warm in compariſon of the Temperature of the other place, where the Soil dos plentifully produce nitrous, and other refrigerating Bodies; though both the places be ſuppoſed to be at the ſame diſtance from the ſurface of the Earth, and conſequently in the ſame Subterraneous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p>Upon the like grounds, it may alſo be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that in the ſame places the Temperature may not be alwaies the ſame, even upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Soil. For I elſewhere ſhew, that ſome Saline Earths, eſpecially nitrous, and ſome mineralls that partake of the nature of marchaſites, admit a kind of graduall maturation, and perhaps other Changes that ſeem to be ſpontaneous. And that ſuch changes happen the more notably in thoſe parts of ſuch Bodies that are expoſed to the Air, as thoſe are that chance to be placed at the ſides of the deep Wells we are talking of. Which things being preſuppoſed, 'twill not be abſurd to conceive, that the minerall, to which either heat or cold is to be referr'd, may be more copious, ripe, and operative at one time, then at another; or that at length, all the Earth capable of being, as it were Aſſimilated by the minerall rudiments harbour'd in it, may be conſumed, or the minerall it ſelfe may arrive at a perfection
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43313:14"/>of maturity, which will make its texture ſo cloſe as to be unfit to be penetrated, and wrought upon, as before, by the water or other Liquor that occaſioned its incaleſcence.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP VII</head>
               <p>I Omit to ſpeak of the tranſient changes that may be occaſion'd in the temperature of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Region of the Earth by ſeverall Accidents, and eſpecially by the Subterraneall Exhalations, that in ſome places and times copiouſly aſcend out of the lower Regions of the Earth. Nor ſhall I inſiſt upon any of the other cauſes of a more durable difference of temper in ſome parts of the ſecond Region, ſuch as may be the Vicinity of Subterraneall Fires in the third Region that heat the incumbent <hi>Soil;</hi> becauſe I would haſten to the Third and laſt part of this Diſcourſe: which yet I muſt not do without premiſing this advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I think my ſelfe oblig'd to ſpeak the more heſitantly and diffidently about the Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature of Subterraneall Air; becauſe mineraliſts have not had the Curioſity to examine it by Weather-glaſſes, which would give us much more truſty Informations then our ſenſe of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling powerfully preaffected by the cold or heat of the externall Air. I did indeed ſend fitt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſome daies journey from this place, to examine the Air at the bottom of ſome of our
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43313:15"/>deep mines: but through ſome unlucky caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties upon the place, the attempt miſcarried. But when I ſhall (God aſſiſting) recover an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity that I have ſince wanted, I hope an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate <hi>ſeal'd Weather-glaſſe,</hi> join'd with a porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Baroſcope will give me better Information then mineraliſts have yet done. I ſay a ſeal'd Weather-glaſſe becauſe though common Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſcopes had been employed by miners, I durſt not rely upon them; being perſwaded by tryalls purpoſely made, as well as by the Reaſon of the thing, of the Fallaciousneſſe of ſuch Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſcopes: for in them the included Air is liable to be wrought upon, not only by the Heat and coldneſſe, but by the weight or Preſſure of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Air. So that if a Thermoſcope be let down from a very conſiderable height, at the top of which the ſtation of the pendulous Liquor be well markt, that Liquor will be found to have riſen, when the Inſtrument reſts at the bottom, as if the included Air were manifeſtly refrigerated: though the temper of the externall Air may be in both places alike, the cauſe of the pendulous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors riſing being indeed that the Aereall pillar incumbent on the ſtagnant Liquor, is higher and heavier at the bottom, where the Inſtrument reſts, then that which lean'd upon it, at its firſt or upper ſtation nearer the top of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſpher. From whence 'twill be eaſy to conclude that at the bottom of a deep Groove, where the Atmoſphericall pillar that preſſes the ſtagnant
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43313:15"/>water will be much longer and heavier then at the top, the Air may appear by the Inſtrument to be colder in places, where 'tis really much hotter, the increaſed weight of the incumbent Air being more forcible to impell up the pendulous Liquor then the indeavour of expanſion procur'd in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Air by the warmth of the place is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>THat which challenges the third and laſt part of my diſcourſe, is the lowermoſt Region of the Earth, about whoſe temperature I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, what I have to ſay in the following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>Propoſition the 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The third Region of the Earth has been obſerved to be conſtantly and ſenſibly warm, but not uniformly ſo; being in ſome places conſiderably hot</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I mention that the recited temperature has been obſerved in the Lower Region, becauſe I would intimate, that I wovld have the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on underſtood with this Limitation, as far as has been yet (that I know of,) obſerved. For all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the deep Grooves that mineraliſts have given us accounts of, and wherein men have wrought long enough to take ſufficient notice of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43313:16"/>the Temperature of the Air, have been made in Soils furniſhed with metalline Oars, or other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls, without which, men would not be invited to be at ſo great a charge, as that of ſinking ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deep pits, and maintaining work-men in them. So that experience has yet but ſlenderly, or at leaſt not ſufficiently informed us of the Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thoſe parts of the third Region of the Earth, that are not furniſhed with ponderous mineralls, and conſequently has not informed us of the Temperature of the Lowermoſt Region in generall; as will better appear by what I ſhall ere long repreſent.</p>
                  <p>Having premiſed this Advertiſement about our propoſition, we may proceed to the diſtinct proofe of the two parts or members it conſiſts of.</p>
                  <p>And to begin with the firſt, whatever the Peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticks teach of the innate Coldneſſe of the Earth, eſpecially where 'tis remoteſt from the mixture of the other Elements; yet having purpoſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of ſeverall perſons that viſited and alſo frequented the Third Region in differing Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Soils, and at differing depths under ground, and Seaſons of the year, I did not perceive that any of them, had ever found it ſenſibly and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome cold in the Third Region of the Earth. And on this occaſion I remember I had ſome light ſuſpition, that (at leaſt in ſome Caſes) the narrowneſs of the Cavities wherein the Diggers were in divers places reduc'd to worke, might
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43313:16"/>make the warmth they felt, proceed in great part from the Steams of their own Bodies, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of the mineralls, and from the Difficulty of cooling or ventilating the Blood in an Air clogg'd with ſteams. And I was the rather induced to thinke this poſſible, becauſe I had (even in metal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line mines that were but ſhallow and very freely acceſſible to the Air) obſerved a ſtrong ſmell of the metall abounding there.</p>
                  <p>I have likewiſe found by ſeverall tryalls, that the exhalations that proceed from the Bodies of Animalls, doe ſo vitiate the Air they abound in, as to make it much leſs fit for their Reſpiration, and to be apt to make them ſick and faint. Wherefore I thought it not altogether unfit to inquire, whether the heat of the Subterraneall air, in ſuch places as have been newly mentioned, might not be referr'd to theſe Cauſes? But I was anſwered in the negative; eſpecially by an inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive perſon that had been in the deepeſt and hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt mines that have been viſited by any Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of mine.</p>
                  <p>This way of accounting for the Subterraneall Warmth being laid aſide, it ſeem'd I confeſſe ſomewhat difficult to conceive how it ſhould be produced; yet two principall Cauſes there are to which I thinke we may probably refer the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of thoſe places, where the air is but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately warm. To which a Third is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; when we come to give an account, why ſome places are troubleſomly hot.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:43313:17"/>
                  <p>And firſt, why the Coldneſſe of Winter ſhould not be felt in the Lowermoſt Region of the Earth may be, that the air there, is too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from the Superterreſtriall air, to be much affected with thoſe adventitious Cauſes of Cold, that make that Quality intenſe in the air above ground. But becauſe this Reaſon ſhews rather, why it ſhould not be in the Earths Lower Region much Colder in <hi>Winter</hi> then in <hi>Summer;</hi> but not why it ſhould be in all ſeaſons warm there, I ſhall add as a Conjecture, that the poſitive cauſe of the actuall warmth may proceed from thoſe deeper parts of the Subterraneall Region, which ly beneath thoſe places which men have yet had occaſion and ability to dig. For it ſeems probable to me, that in theſe yet inpenetrated Bowells of the Earth, there are great ſtore-houſes of either actuall Fires, or places conſiderably Hot, or, (in ſome Regions) of both; from which <hi>Reconditories</hi> (if I may ſo call them) or magazines of hypogeall heat, that quality is communicated, eſpecially by Subterraneall Channells, Clefts, Fibres, or other Conveyances, to the leſs deep parts of the Earth, either by a propagation of heat through the ſubſtance of the interpoſed part of the Soil. (as when the upper part of an Oven is remiſsly heated by the ſame Agents that produce an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe heat in the Cavity,) or by a more eaſy diffuſion of the Fire or heat through the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned Conveyances as may be exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified by the pipes that convey heat in ſome Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43313:17"/>ſtructures:) Or elſe, (which is perhaps the moſt uſuall way,) by ſending upwards hot minerall Exhalations and Steams, which by reaſon of the comparatively heavy materialls they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of, and by reaſon of their being leſſe diſperſed nearer the places whence they proceed, are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally more plentifull in the deeper parts of the Earth, and ſomewhat affect them with the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that they brought from the workhouſes where they were form'd and that they retain for ſome time after.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>THat manifeſt Steams oftentimes are found in Grooves, eſpecially in deep ones is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, by the damps that infeſt moſt of them, and that in diſtant Regions, as in ſeverall provinces of <hi>Germany, Bohemia, Hungary,</hi> &amp;c. as alſo in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts of <hi>England</hi> in Grooves, ſome of which I have received Relations from the mine-men themſelves. By which it appears, that ſeverall of theſe Exhalations aſcending from the entralls of the Earth are ſulphureous &amp; Bituminous in ſmell and in ſome Grooves (one whereof I elſewhere mention my ſelfe to have viſited) theſe Steams are apt, actually to take fire.</p>
               <p>The warmth of many Subterraneall Exhations I thinke may be made further probable by ſome other Obſervations. For though theſe newly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43313:18"/>mentioned are not to be rejected, and may be employed for want of better; yet I have ſeverall times queſtioned, whether I ought to acquieſce in them alone. For I do not thinke the eaſy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammableneſs of Bodies to be alwaies a ſure proofe of the actuall ſenſible warmth of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute parts it conſiſts of, or may be reduced into. For though Salt-peter be very inflammable, yet being by a ſolution in fair water reduced to invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Corpuſcles, it highly refrigerates that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor. Nor have I obſerved its fumes, (when far from the Fire,) to have any heat ſenſible to our Touch. And the like may be ſaid of the Exhalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of highly rectifi'd ſpirit of Wine; which yet we know is itſelfe totally inflammable. Nay I know not whether, (for a Reaſon elſewhere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared) copious Exhalations may not aſcend from the lower parts of the Earth, and yet be rather Cold then Hot. For (in another Paper) I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a way by which I made a mixture that plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully enough enitted Steams, of whoſe being ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Cold, then hot nature, there was this probability, that the mixture whence they aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded even whilſts its component Ingredients were briskly acting upon one another, was not only ſenſibly, but conſiderably Cold.</p>
               <p>One main thing therefore that induces me to aſſent to the Opinion, whereto the former Inſtances do but incline me, is, That having purpoſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of an obſerving man that frequented deep mines, (wherein he had a conſiderable ſhare,)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43313:18"/>he anſwered me, that he plainly obſerved the fumes that came out of the mouths of the deep pits, to be actually and ſenſibly warm, and that in a warm ſeaſon of the year. And <hi>Morinus</hi> (above cited) ſpeaking of the deep <hi>Hungarian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines,</hi> makes it the firſt Epithite of the copious Exhalation that aſcended from the bottom, that it was <hi>hot.</hi> And a few pages after he ſays, that at the mouth of the Well, the aſcending Fumes were <hi>ſenſibly hot in Summer it ſelfe.</hi> And the ſame Arguments that I have elſewhere given to ſhew that there are very hot places, and as it were Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuary in the Bowells of the Earth, may ſerve to make it probable that the ſteams aſcending thence may be actually warm.</p>
               <p>That alſo in many places of the Earth, where no Grooves are dugg, and no viſible Exhalations are taken notice of, they may yet pervade the Soil, and exerciſe ſome operations of warmth, may be probable by this, that the experienced <hi>Agricola</hi> himſelfe reckons it among the ſigns of a latent minerall vein, that the hoar-froſt does not ly upon that tract of the Surface of the Earth, under which a vein (though perhaps very deep) runs. The like Directions I have known given by the skillfull in <hi>England,</hi> for the Diſcovery of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that contain Coal-mines. And I remember a near relation of mine ſhewed me a great ſcope of Land of his, which (though in an outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, likely to be as cold as any place there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts,) he affirm'd would not ſuffer Snow to ly
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43313:19"/>upon it above a day or two in the midſt of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The probability of which Relation was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to me by the anſwer I received from a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ingenious Gentleman who lives among mines, and is not a little concern'd in ſome of them. For having inquired of him, What he had obſerved about the lying, or not lying of the <hi>Snow</hi> on the minerall Soils near the place of his Reſidence; he replyed, that in ſome of them, he did not take notice of any peculiar Indiſpoſition to let the Ice and Snow continue on them; which I conceive may proceed, either from the want of ſuch mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls in the Subjacent parts, as were then in the ſtate of Incaleſcence; or elſe from this that, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what we have elſewhere obſerved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Snows on <hi>Aetna</hi>) the direct aſcenſion of the hot Steams was hindered by ſome Layers of Rocks or other Stone, through which the Steams could not penetrate, or could doe it but ſo ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as to looſe their actuall warmth by the way. But this Gentleman added that in other places, near that of his abode, and ſuch as he knew to have minerall-Veins beneath them, he obſerved that the Snow, (nor the Ice) would ſcarce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue at all upon the Surface of the Ground, even in an extraordinarily cold winter.</p>
               <p>It will be a conſiderable Inſtance to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe if it be indeed true which ſome learned men have written that near the Gold-mines in Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43313:19"/>the leaves of the trees, (eſpecially thoſe that reſpct the Ground) are oftentimes found en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobled with a golden-colour from the metalline Exhalations of the Gold-mines; which one would think muſt by reaſon of their ponderousneſſe need a conſiderable heat to elevate them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally into the open Air. But though doubting of this Relation, as not made by mineraliſts or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Obſervers, I inquired about it of a perſon, whoſe Curioſity carried him purpoſely to viſit thoſe mines, I was anſwerd that he could not be a witneſſe to the truth of the Obſervation; yet he told me, an obſervation (which <hi>I</hi> elſe where men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that doth not diſcountenance that Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
               <p>If it be objected that what has hitherto been ſaid about Latent Fires and heats in the Bowells of the Earth will give an account of the warmth only of thoſe places that are within teach of the action of ſuch Magazines of heat, which probably may be wanting in many places of the Earth, I ſhall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily confeſſe, that as I firſt made this Objection to my ſelfe, ſo I do not yet diſcern it to be unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and that for ought I know if men had occaſion to digg as deep and be as far converſant in many other low places of the Earth, where there are no ſigns of Mineralls, as they have done where the hopes of actuall diſcovery of veins of metalls, and other mineralls worth working, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited them, divers places in the Third Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Earth would be met with, that would
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43313:20"/>bedeſtitute of the warmth that has hitherto been generally found in places of the ſame Region that either abound with mineralls themſelves, or are near ſome of the deep and latent Aeſtuaries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-mentioned.</p>
               <p>And as for thoſe parts of the Third Region of the Earth, which men feel not only warm, but troubleſomly hot, that incommodious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of heat ſeems not, (at leaſt in ſome places) to be derivable from the two above mentioned cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; which muſt, (to produce ſo conſiderable an effect) be aſſiſted by a third cauſe more potent then themſelves: which ſeems to be the inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcence there is produced in many mines, and other Places, by the mutuall action of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent parts promoted by water of immature and more looſely contexted mineralls, eſpecially ſuch as are of a Marchaſiticall nature. That ſuch an Incaleſcence may by ſuch a way be produced in the Bowells of the Earth, I have elſewhere ſhewn (in my diſcourſe of Subterraneall Fires &amp; heats) by the examples of ſuch incaleſcences pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible in minerall Bodies here above ground. That Marchaſites which for the moſt part abound in Vitrioll, are bodies very fit to procure this Subterraneall heat, may be conſirm'd not only by the Sulphureous and Saline parts they abound with, and by this, that many of them may be wrought on, as we have tryed, both by ſimple water, and even by moiſt Air, which argues the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolubleneſſe of their Conſtitution: but alſo by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43313:20"/>this, that having purpoſely inquired of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman that went out of Curioſity to viſit one of the deeper Hungarian mines, he confirmed to me what I had otherwiſe been informed of, by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering me, that in the lower parts of the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, he had gathered Vitrioll that app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ared above ground to be of a golden nature; and that in a Cave that is on one ſide of the Groove, in the deep Gold-mine near <hi>Cremnitzo,</hi> the corroſive ſmell is ſo ſtrong and noxious, that men have not dared to dig out the native Gold it richly abounds with, being deterr'd by the ill fate of livers that ventured to work in it. Adding that though he paſſed by it, in great haſt; yet he could not avoid the being offended by the noyſome Exhalations. And on this occaſion, 'twill not be (I preſume) diſliked, if I illuſtrate what I was ſaving of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature mineralls, by ſubjoining, That having, asked this Chymiſt whether the Vitrioll he found very deep underground were all ſolid, or ſome of it ſoft? he affirm'd that as he gathered it, he found ſome of it ſoft. And to ſatisfy my curioſity to know whether it continued that yeilding conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence? he further told me, that it was ſoft in the deeper part of the mine, but when he had brought it into the Superterreſtriall Air, it hardened there and appeared to have 9 divers golden ſtreakes in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>ONe thing there is, which muſt not be here
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43313:21"/>omitted, though it will probably be great news to thoſe that philoſophize only in their ſtudies, and have not received information from any that viſited the deeper parts of the Earth: The <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menon</hi> is this, That the Diggers in mines having found by unwelcom experience that in deep Grooves, the Air (unleſs ventilated and renewed) dos in a ſhort time become unfit for reſpiration, have been put upon this expedient, to ſinke at ſome convenient diſtance from the Groove where the miners worke, another pit (by ſome called a vent pitt) that uſually tends directly downwards (though ſometimes it make Angels) to which our Engliſh-minemen do in ſeverall parts of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom give differing names; whereof the moſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſicant ſeems to be that given it in the Leadmines of <hi>Darbyſhire,</hi> where they call it an <hi>Air-ſhaft,</hi> and are wont to make it 40, 50, and ſometimes 80 or 100 paces off, and, (as one of the cheife and skillfull Miners there informed me) as deep as the Groove or Well; (Though I find that the beſt <hi>German</hi> and ſome <hi>Engliſh Miners</hi> think a leſs depth will often ſuffice) From this Air-ſhaft to the Groove the men work in, there paſſes a Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell or if I may ſo call it, <hi>Ventiduct</hi> to convey the Air from the former to the latter; which is that, that <hi>Agricola</hi> ſometimes (for he employs not the Terme alwaies in the ſame ſenſe) denotes by his <hi>Cuniculu;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. V. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> VI. De re metall.</note> and which though differingly nam'd by our Miners in ſeverall parts of England
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43313:21"/>is in the above mentioned Lead-mines called a <hi>Drift,</hi> becauſe the Air dos uſually in the form of Wind drive thorow it: and thereby enables the Workmen to breath freely and conveniently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogh at the very bottom of the Well. On this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion I remember that a very obſervingrman who much frequented theſe Mines told me, that at the depth of no leſs then about 200 yards, be found that by the help of the Air-ſhaft, the Air was not only very commodious for Reſpiration, but tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate as to heat and Cold. And when I further asked, what time of the year it then was? he told me 'twas about the latter end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> and the beginning of <hi>September.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that which ſeems to me to deſerve a farther and accurate obſervation about the motion and Temperature of the Air in theſe Artificiall under ground Cavities, is a Relation of <hi>Agricolas</hi> which, (though he be the moſt Claſſick Author we have about m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes,) has not (that I know of) been taken notice of, in him. For this experienced VVritter, though in his Treatiſe
<note n="*" place="margin">Idcirco f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>robes, putei cuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſi complentur exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riore Aere. Atque ipſum in cos influere imprimis hyema li tempore evidens eſt in duobus puteis, ad quorum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trumque ex modico interval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h cuniculus aliquis pertinet. Nam Aer in unum continuo influit rectâque per cunicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m permeat &amp; tranſit ad alterum; atque ex eo rurſus evolat foras.</note> 
                  <hi>de Ortu &amp; cauſis Subterraneo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> he only ſayes indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, that by means of the <hi>Cuniculus or Driſt,</hi> which connects the Air-ſhaft &amp; the well, that Air which comes in at one of thoſe two, paſſes out at the other; yet in his Fifth Book
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43313:22"/>
                  <hi>de re metallicâ</hi> he gives a more particular and odd account of the courſe of the Air in theſe not over clear Terms, <hi>Aer autem exterior ſe ſuâ ſponte ſundit in cava terra, atque cum per ea penetrare poteſt, rur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus evolat ſoras. Sed diverſâ ratione hoc ſieri ſolet; etenim vernis &amp; aeſtivis diebus in altiorem puteum influit, &amp; per cuniculum vel foſſam latentem perme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, ac ex humiliori effluit ſimiliter iiſdem diebus in altiorem cuniculum infunditur, &amp; interjecto puteo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluit in humiliorem cuniculum atque ex eo emanat. Autumnali verò &amp; hyberno tempore, contra in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niculum vel puteum humiliorem intrat, &amp; ex altiori exit: verum ea fluxionum Aeris mutatio in tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Regionibus fit in initio veris, &amp; in fine Antumni: in frigidis autem, in fine veris &amp; in in initio Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumni.</hi> To which he adds that which is more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable; That the Air in both the mentioned times,
<note place="margin">Sed Aer utroque tempore an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teaquam curſum ſuum illum conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etum co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> teneat plerum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erum ſpacio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> habet mutationes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ltiorem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>el cuniculum inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, modo in humiliorem.</note> before its wonted courſe come to be dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſetled, uſes to be for the ſpace of a fortnight li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to frequent changes, ſometimes flowing into the upper or higher groove or Drift, and ſometimes into the lower, (and paſſing out at the other.) If this Obſervation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly hold, though but in ſome deep Mines, it may hint ſome odd inquiries, about conſiderable and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> changes in the Subterraneall parts of the Earth, or in the Air, or in Both, which though they have not yet been conſidered, deſerve
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43313:22"/>be ſo. I have endeavoured to learn whether any ſuch thing has been obſerved in ſome deep Lead-mines, whence I have procured divers informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about other particulars. But a very obſerving Perſon, that had the chief hand in contriving the Subterraneall ſtructures there, aſſured me that both VVinter and Summer, the current of Air, went conſtantly the ſame way: the Air entring in at the Mouth of the <hi>Air-ſhaft,</hi> and coming out at the <hi>Perpendicular Groove,</hi> which takes its deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination from a <hi>Cave,</hi> (or <hi>Caſa Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ealas</hi>) uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally built over the Orifice of it, to ſhelter the Workmen from rain, and other inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>And ſince the writing of this, I found in <hi>Mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> (his Relation already mentioned) a paſſage that may ſomewhat illuſtrate the darkly expreſt Obſervation of <hi>Agricola.</hi> For the lately men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd Author writes, that in the deep <hi>Hungarian</hi>-Mines he viſited, the outward Air paſſed (firſt) through the Burrows, and ſo through By waies, (if I may ſo call them) that tended not directly downwards, reacht at length to the bottom of the VVell, or perpendicular Groove, whence, together with the Steams proceeding from the Mine) is aſcended ſtrait upwards. But <hi>Morinus</hi> taking no notice at all of <hi>Agricola's</hi> Obſervation about the differing courſe of the Subterraneall Air at differing Seaſons of the year: <hi>though</hi> (as I find by what he writes elſewhere,) 'twas Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer when he viſited the Mines, and ſo what he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43313:23"/>reports, agrees well with one part of what <hi>Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cola</hi> ſeems to ſay; <hi>yet,</hi> as to the other, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall part of his Obſervation, he ſays not any thing. And the ſenſible heat he aſcribes to the ſteams aſcending out of the perpendicular Well, leaves it ſomewhat dubious, what intereſt the Rarefaction of the Air, by the Subterraneous Heat may have in the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> we have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of.</p>
               <p>But to return to what I was ſaying before I had occaſion to mention <hi>Morinus.</hi> Which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it will not be impertinent to add, that I loarn'd by inquiry, that the <hi>Air-ſhafts,</hi> and the Wells, were in theſe Mines much of a depth. But I hope ere long to have accounts of what happens in other mines, in other parts of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as to the courſe of the Subterraneall Air eſpecially when its iſſuing out of the Well, or the <hi>Air-ſhaft</hi> depend not on the changes of the Winds that blow above ground: And I wiſh the curious would employ the like endeavours in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries.</p>
               <p>For indeed what I have hitherto diſcourſed in this Treatiſe, is <hi>accommodated</hi> but to the ſcant Information I have hitherto receiv'd; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought to be <hi>rectified</hi> or <hi>Confirmed</hi> by farther Informations if they can be procur'd.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, I think I may probably e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, gather from the pas't Diſcourſe, that though in ſome Mines, three Subterraneall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, and their diſtinguiſhing Attributes, may
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43313:23"/>be not inconveniently aſſigned; yet generally ſpeaking of the whole Body of the Terreſtriall Globe (as farr as we know it) both the Bounds and the Temperature of the Regions of the Earth, as well as thoſe of the Air, are various and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain enough.</p>
               <p>And much leſs have we any certain knowledge of the Temperature of the more inward, and (if I may ſo ſpeak) the more Centrall parts of the Earth; in which, whether there be not a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſolidity, or great Tracts of Fluid matter, and whether or no, differing Regions are to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, and what their number, Order, thickneſs, and qualifications may be, we are as yet ignorant, and ſhall I fear long continue ſo, For it is to be noted (with which obſervation I ſhall conclude) that what has been hitherto diſcourſed, belongs only to the Temper of thoſe Subterraneall parts, to which men have been enabled to reach by Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 'Tis true indeed that ſome Mines eſpecially in Germany, and Hungary are of a Stupendious depth, in compariſon of the generality of ours, and of the more obvious Cavities of the Earth; yet I find it boaſted in a Diſcourſe written purpoſely of the Various Mines, in the VVorld, that the rich Mine at Sueberg is 400 yards deep: And they are ſcarce believed, that relate one Hungarian-Mine which they viſited to be 400 ſathom; which though double the depth of the former, reaches not to half a mile. But the deepeſt of all the mines that I have as yet read or heard of, from any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43313:24"/>Relator, is that which the experienced <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricola</hi> in the Tract he calls <hi>Bermannus, Cap.</hi> 12. mentions to be at <hi>Cotteberg.</hi> But this it ſelf though it reach to above 500 fathom, that is, 3000 foot, yet this prodigious depth dos not much exceed halfe a mile &amp; fals ſhort of three quarters,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Licet variae de ambitu ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae opiniones ſint, nobis ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men propemodum conſtet, eſſe ipſam milliarum</hi> Italia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum 26255, <hi>quod in maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ad Terrae ſuperficiem cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo reſpondeant uni gradui milliaria proximè</hi> 73. <hi>&amp;c. Gaſſend. Inſtit. Aſtronom. Lib:</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 13.</note> and how ſmall a part is that of the whole depth of the Terreſtriall Globe? whoſe ſemidiame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if we admit the recent account of the Learned <hi>Gaſſendus,</hi> reckoned at 4177. Italian miles: in compariſon of which, (as I was ſaying), how ſmall a thing is a depth that falls very ſhort of a ſingle mile?</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:43313:24"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:25"/>
            <head>Of the TEMPERATURE Of the SUBMARINE REGIONS As to <hi>HEAT</hi> and <hi>COLD.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:43313:26"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43313:26"/>
               <head>OF THE TEMPERATURE, Of the SUBMARINE REGIONS. <hi>As to Heat and Cold.</hi> CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THough the <hi>Ariſtotelians</hi> who believe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Aire to be reciprocally trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, doe thereby fancy an Affinity between them, that I am not yet convinced of: yet I readily allow of ſo much Affinity betwixt thoſe two fluid Bodies, as invites me (after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving treated of the Temperature of the Aeriall Regions) to ſay ſomething of that of the Submarine Regions: which name of <hi>Submarine,</hi> though I know it may ſeem Improper, I therefore Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not to make uſe of, becauſe even among the Generality of Learned Men uſe has Authorized the name of <hi>Subterraneous Places.</hi> For as theſe are not by this name, and indeed cannot in Reaſon be ſuppoſed to be beneath the whole Bodie of the Earth, but only the <hi>Superficiall</hi> parts of it: ſo by the Appellation of <hi>Submarine Regions</hi> 'tis not to be ſuppoſed that the places ſo called are below
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43313:27"/>the Bottom of the <hi>Sea,</hi> but only below the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of it.</p>
               <p>But to come from words to things, I preſume it will not be expected that I that never pretended to be a Diver ſhould give of the Regions I am to treat of, an Account build on my own Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and I hope it may gratifie a Reaſonable Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity about a ſubject, of which Claſſick Authors are ſo very ſilent, and about which Philoſophers ſeeme not ſo much as to have attempted any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments (for want of Opportunities and mean to make them.) I offer the beſt Information I could ſupply my ſelfe what by purpoſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with Perſons that have dived ſome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and ſome by the help of <hi>Engins.</hi> To which I have added ſome reports that I judge fit to be allowed, made me by Perſons that had converſed with the Divers upon thoſe Affrican and Indian-Coaſts, where the moſt famous and expert are thought to be found.</p>
               <p>And I the rather report the Anſwers and Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onsmy Inquiries procur'd becauſe the Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they give us concerne a ſubject conſiderable as well as vaſt, about which nevertheleſſe I among many others am not in a condition to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisſie at all my Curioſity by Tryalls of my own making, and becauſe alſo what I ſhall ſay will probably ſpoile the credit of the Vulgar Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror that in all deepe water of which the Sea is the Cheifeſt, the lowermoſt are ſtill the warmeſt parts, unleſſe in caſe that in ſome very hot Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43313:27"/>or ſeaſons, the ſuperficiall ones happen to be a little warm'd by the Extraordinary or Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent heat of the <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. <hi>II</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough the Air and the Earth have been diſcriminated as to Temperature into three Regions; yet the Informations I have hitherto met with, invite me not to aſſign to the <hi>Sea</hi> any more then two. The former of which may be ſuppoſed to reach from the ſuperficies of it, as far downwards as the manifeſt operation of the variouſly reflected and refracted Beames of the <hi>Sun,</hi> or other Cauſes of warmth penetrates: from which to the Bottom of the <hi>Sea,</hi> the other Region may be ſuppoſed to extend.</p>
               <p>According to this Diviſion the Limits of this upper Region will not be alwaies conſtant; for in the Torrid Zone and other hotter Climates, it will, <hi>Caeteris paribus,</hi> be greater then in the Frigid Zone or in the Temperate Zones: and ſo it will be in <hi>Summer</hi> then in <hi>Winter:</hi> and in hot weather then in Cold; ſuppoſing in theſe Caſes the Heat to come from the Sun and Air; and not, as ſometimes it may do, from the Subterraneall Exhalations.</p>
               <p>The ſame cauſes are likewiſe proper as 'tis manifeſt to alter the Temperature as well as the Bounds of this Region, But this Temperature
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43313:28"/>may alſo be changed in ſome few places by at leaſt two other Cauſes; The one is the differing conſtitution of the Soil that compoſes the Shore, which may affect the neighbouring water if it doe extraordinarily abound with Nitre, looſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texed marchaſites, or other ſubſtances capable conſiderably to encreaſe or leſſen the Coldneſſe of the water. Another though unfrequent Cauſe, may be the figure and ſituation of the leſſe deep parts of the Shore, which may in ſome ſort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberate the Heat that proceeds from the <hi>Sun;</hi> and upon ſuch an account may either add to the warmth, or allay the Coldneſſe that would elſe be found in the neighbouring water. For whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Schools</hi> are wont to teach about the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Attrition of Air in the heat produced by the <hi>Sun Beams,</hi> I have elſewhere ſhown by Experiments, that thoſe Beams may conſiderably operate upon Bodies placed quite under water.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe two Caſes that may occaſion Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions to the generall Obſervation; I intimated by the words, <hi>at leaſt,</hi> that there might be others. Becauſe, to mention now but one Example, though it ſeem probable from what I have elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where delivered concerning the <hi>Subterraneall</hi> Fires and Heats, that may in ſome places be met with, even beneath the bottom of the <hi>Sea,</hi> that the <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> I am going to recite may be reduc'd to the cauſes newly intimated; <hi>yet</hi> I am not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly certain but that in this caſe, whereto ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may perhaps be found reſebling, ſome other
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43313:28"/>cauſe, then thoſe hitherto mentioned, may produce or concurre to the effect. The Relation here meant is afforded us by the following Paſſage, taken out of the Voyage of <hi>Monſieur de Monts</hi> into <hi>New-France,</hi> (whereof he went to be Governor) where the Relator thus recites his obſervation. <hi>About the eighteenth day of June we found the Sea-water</hi> during three dayes ſpace very warm, and by the ſame warmth, our wine alſo was warme in the bottom of our ſhip; yet the Air was no hotter then before. And the 21 of the ſaid moneth, quite contrary, we were 2 or 3 days ſo much compaſſed with miſts and cold, that we thought our ſelves to be in the moneth of <hi>January,</hi> and the water of the <hi>Sea</hi> was extreame cold: which continued with us untill we came upon the Bank by reaſon of the ſaid miſts, which outwardly did procure this cold unto us. This effect he attributes to a kind of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiperiſtaſis in the following part of his narrative; which I ſhal not now either tranſcribe or examine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3</head>
               <p>And thus much being breifely noted touching the upper Region of the <hi>Sea,</hi> and the requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Cautions (that may perhaps extend further then it) being premiſed; it remains that I take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the Temperature of the Lower Region, which, in one word, is Cold (unleſſe in ſome few places to be preſently mentioned.) For water be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43313:29"/>in it's naturall or moſt ordinary ſtate, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor whoſe parts are more ſlowly agitated then thoſe of mens Organs of Feeling, muſt be upon that account Cold as to ſenſe: and conſequently it need not be ſtrange that thoſe parts of the Sea, which are too remote to be ſenſibly agitated by the Sun-Beams, or wrought upon by the warmth which the Air and upper parts of the Earth may from other Cauſes receive, ſhould be felt Cold by thoſe that deſcend into it; unleſſe in thoſe few places where the Coldneſſe may be either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd or allay'd by hot Springs or Subterreſtriall Exhalations, flowing or aſcending from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Earth, or the lower parts of the ſhore into the incumbent or adjacent parts of the water.</p>
               <p>To juſtifie my aſcribing of this Coldneſſe to the ſecond, or lower Region of the Sea, I ſhall now ſubjoin ſome Relations I procur'd from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that had occaſion to goe down into it, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwaies take notice of its Temperature in very differing Regions of the World, and at very une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall depths.</p>
               <p>And firſt as to the Temperature of the lower Region in the <hi>Northerne Sea,</hi> I had the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to converſe often, and ſometimes to oblige a man bold and curious enough, who for ſome years got the beſt part of his ſubſiſtence by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to the bottom of the Sea in an Engin, whoſe ſtructure I elſewhere deſcribe, to ſeek for, and recover Goods loſt in Shipwrackt Veſſels. This perſon I diligently examined about divers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43313:29"/>
                  <hi>Submarine Phaenomena,</hi> about which his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers may be elſewhere met with. And as to the Temperature of the lower parts of the Sea (the knowledge of which is that alone that concerns us in this place) he ſeverall times complained to me of the Coldneſſe of the deep water, which kept him from being able to ſtay in it ſo long as he might have been put into a condition of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the goodneſſe of his Engin; for I remember that he related to me that he ſtaid once betwixt an hour or two, at a depth that was no greater then 14 foot and a half upon the coaſt of Sweden, in a place that was near the ſhore; and I after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards learnd that he ſtaid much longer in a dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place; (uſe having probably made the Cold more ſupportable to him) He told me then, that about two years before he was engaged by a good reward to goe down with his Engin to the bottom of the Sea to fetch up ſome Goods of value out of a Ship that had been caſt away there within a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a miles diſtance from a very little Iſland, and if I miſtake not about 6 miles from the Shore. He farther anſwered me that though he felt it not at all Cold on the Surface of the Water (his attempt being made in <hi>June</hi>) yet about the depth of the Ship, it was ſo very Cold, that he felt it not ſo Cold in <hi>England</hi> Winter and Froſty VVeather. And he told me that an exceſſive Cold was there felt not only by him but by very ſturdy men, who invited by his example, would needs alſo goe down themſelves to participate and promote the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43313:30"/>hoped for Diſcovery. He told me alſo, that the upper water did but cool and refreſh him; but the deeper he went the Colder he felt it, which is the more conſiderable, becauſe he had ſome times occaſion to ſtay at 10 fathoms or even 80 foot under water. And I ſince found that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed divers Virtuoſi, that purpoſely conſulted him, that he found the Coldneſſe of the Water encreaſe with its depth: and gave that for the reaſon why he could not ſtay ſo many hours as otherwiſe he might, at the bottom of the Sea. Adding that before his Engin was well fitted, he was once ſo covered over with it, that he was forced to touch the ground with his hands and feet, and the neighbouring parts, to which he found a Coldneſſe communicated by the <hi>Fundus</hi> he lean'd upon; though the cloſeneſſe of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered Engin made the other, and (whilſt he was in that poſture) upper parts of his Body, of a very differing Temper.</p>
               <p>An inquiſitive perſon of my acquaintance that made a long ſtay in the <hi>Northerne America</hi> (at about two or three and forty degrees of Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude) and diverted himſelfe often with ſwimming under water, anſwered me, that though he ſcarce remembred himſelfe to have dived above two fathoms beneath the ſurface of the <hi>Sea;</hi> yet even at that ſmall depth, he obſerved the water to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in coldneſſe, the lower he deſcended into it. Which argues, that though the Sun-Beams do often penetrate plentifully enough to carry light
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43313:30"/>to a great depth under water; yet they doe not alwaies carry with them a ſenſible heat: and that at leaſt in ſome places, the upper Region of the <hi>Sea</hi> reaches but a little way.</p>
               <p>The coldneſſe of the Climate in theſe weſtern parts of Europe, and the want of conſiderable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements to invite men to dive often to any great depth into our Seas, has kept me from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to procure many obſervations about the temperature of their lower Region, but upon the hotter Coaſts of Africk, and the Eaſt-Indies, the frequent Invitations men have to dive for Corall, pearles, and other <hi>Submarine Productions,</hi> has made it poſſible for me to get more numerous obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: ſome of which I ſhall now annex.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <p>MEeting with a Perſon of Quality who had been preſent at the ſiſhing of Corall upon the ſhoar of Africa, and Who was himſelfe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in diving, I inquired of him whether he found the <hi>Sea</hi> upon the African Coaſt to be much colder at a good depth, then nearer the ſurface; whereto he anſwered me, that though he had ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome dived above three or four fathoms deep, yet at that depth he found it ſo much colder then nearer the Top of the water, that he could not well endure the coldneſſe of it.</p>
               <p>And when I farther asked him whether when he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43313:31"/>was let down to the bottom of the <hi>Sea</hi> in a great diving Bell (as he told me he had been) he felt it very cold, though the water could not come im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to touch him, he replyed that when the bell came firſt to the ground, he found the Air in it very cold, though after he had ſtaid a while there, his breath and the ſteams of his Body made him very hot.</p>
               <p>That alſo at a greater depth in thoſe hotter Climates the <hi>Sea-water</hi> is ſenſibly Cold may be thus made probable, Inquiring of a famous Sea-Commander who had been upon the Affrican Coaſt, to what depth he was wont to ſinck his Bottles to preſerve his Wine any thing coole in that exceſſive hot Climate, he Anſwered me that in the day time he kept it in a tolerable temper ſo as to be drinkable, by keeping it in the Bottom of the ſhip, and in ſand, but in the morning he had it coole enough by ſincking his Bottles over night into the <hi>Sea,</hi> and letting them hang all night at 20 or 30 fathom deepe under water.</p>
               <p>Inquiring alſo of an intelligent Gentleman that was imploy'd to the river of Gambra, &amp; ſayl'd up 700 miles in it, in a ſmall frigot, whether he had obſerved that in the <hi>Sea,</hi> even of thoſe hot climats, wine may be preſerved coole, he told me that it might, and that by the means I hinted to him, which was to let down when the ſhip came to an Anchor in the Evening ſeverall Bottles full of wine (they uſed that of <hi>Madera</hi>) exactly ſtoped to ten, 12, or 14 fathoms deep, whence being the next
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43313:31"/>morning drawn up, they found the wine coole and freſh (as if the veſſels had been in theſe parts drawne up out of a well) provided it were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently drink, for if that Circumſtance were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, the heat of the Aire on the upper part of the water would quickly warme the Liquor.</p>
               <p>I remember too, that having met with a man of Letters that ſail'd to the Eaſt-Indies in a <hi>Portugal-Caraet,</hi> I learnt by enquiry of him, that 'twas the practice in that great Veſſell for the Captain and other Perſons of note, whilſt they paſſe through the Torrid Zone, to keep their Drink, whether Wine or Water, cool, by letting it down in bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles to the depth of 80, 90, anc ſometimes an hundred Fathom or better, and letting it ſtay there a competent time; after which he told me he found it to be exceeding cool and refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, to ſatisfie my ſelfe as far as I could, to how great a depth the Coldneſſ of the Sea rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched; meeting an obſerving Traveller whoſe affairs or Curioſity had carried him to divers parts both of the Eaſt and VVeſt-Indies, I enquired of him whether he had taken notice of any extraordinary deep ſoundings in the vaſter ſeas, To which being anſwered, that ſome years agoe ſailing to the Eaſt Indies in a very great ſhip, over a place on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the Line that was ſuſpected to be very deep, they had the Curioſity to let down 400 Fathom of Line, and found they needed no leſſe. Whereupon I enquired of him, whether he had
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43313:32"/>taken notice of the Temperature of the ſounding Lead aſſoon as 'twas drawn up: To which he told me, that he, and ſome others did; and that the Lead which was of the weight of about 30, or 35 l, had received ſo intenſe a degree of coldneſſe as was very remarkable; inſomuch that he thought that if it had been a maſſe of Ice, it could not have more vehemently refrigerated his hands: and when I asked in what Climate this obſervation was made, he told me 'twas in the Antarctick Hemiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phere, but at a great diſtance from the Line. As indeed I concluded by ſome Circumſtances he mentioned to me, that 'twas about the 35th de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Southern Latitude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <p>Theſe are the cheife Relations I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been able to procure about the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature of the <hi>Sea;</hi> which if they be ſo confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by others, as that we may conclude they will generally hold; it wil not be irrational to conceive that in reference to Temperature, thoſe two Fluids, <hi>Air</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> may have this in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that where their <hi>Surfaces</hi> are contiguous, and in the neighbouring parts, they happen to be ſometimes cold, and ſometimes hot, as the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles they conſiſt of, chance to be more or leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated by the variouſly reflected <hi>Sun-Beams,</hi> or more or leſſe affected by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther cauſes of Heat.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43313:32"/>But that part of the Air which they call the ſecond, &amp; is ſuperior to the firſt, as alſo the lower Region of the Sea, being more remote from the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe cauſes, doe retain their naturall or more undiſturbed Temperature, which, as to us men, is a conſiderable degree of coldneſs, the Agitation of their ſmall parts being uſually in thoſe Regions much inferior to that of the <hi>Spirits, Blood,</hi> &amp; other parts of our Organs of Feeling. <hi>So</hi> that the Regions of the <hi>water</hi> and <hi>Air</hi> ſeem to anſwer one another; but in an inverted order of ſituation, and the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> might perhaps be carryed further, if I had time and opportunity to doe it in this place. And here I ſhall not diſſemble that I was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what perplexed by meeting with a traveller that had viſited the Eaſt-<hi>Indian Coaſt,</hi> near the famous <hi>Cape</hi> of <hi>Comory:</hi> for asking him ſome queſtions touching the neighbouring <hi>Sea, I gathered</hi> from his diſcourſe, that he concluded from that of ſome Divers, that the <hi>Sea</hi> near <hi>Ceylom</hi> was warmer at the bottom then at the top. And when I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon asked him <hi>whether</hi> this happened not in their <hi>Winter,</hi> he replyed that it was indeed Winter, though not with us, yet with them; it occurr'd indeed to my thoughts on this occaſion, that perhaps in a part of the Torrid Zone ſo near the Line as about 80 degrees, if the <hi>Sea</hi> were not of a conſiderable depth, the heat of the two not far diſtant ſhores of <hi>Coromandell</hi> and <hi>Ceylom</hi> might have no ſmall influence upon the Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tature of the water. I conſidered alſo (which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43313:33"/>did not a little weigh with me) that in divers parts of the Eaſt-Indies, and even in a Region bordering upon <hi>Coromandell,</hi> where an ingenious Acquaintance of mine lived ſome years, it has been obſerved, that <hi>Winter</hi> and <hi>Summer</hi> are not ſo much diſcriminated by Cold weather &amp; Hot, as by very Rainy weather and very dry. Nay in ſome places the ſultry heat of the Climate is more complained of, in what they call their <hi>Winter</hi> then their <hi>Summer.</hi> So that there will be no neceſſity to recur to an <hi>Antiperiſtaſis</hi> occaſioned by the coldnes of the <hi>Winter.</hi> I thought too, that it may perhaps be without abſurdity ſuſpected, that as the bottom of the <hi>Sea</hi> in this place had a peculiar Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that fitted it more then others for the copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous production of pearls: ſo there might be ſome peculiarity in the nature of the ſubjacent Soil, or there may be ſome Subterraneali Fire or heat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath it, which may occaſion an unuſuall warmth in that part of the Sea, by w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> cheriſhing warmth, perhaps ſuch abundance of ſhell Fiſhes teeming with pearls, may be invited to ſettle there rather then in any of the neighbouring places. But with all theſe conjectures, I ſhould not have been ſo well ſatisfied, as with the anſwer I afterwards ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by a Gentleman whoſe Curioſity had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him to be an aſſiduous <hi>Spectator</hi> of the famous pearl-fiſhing near the <hi>Iſland</hi> of Manar; between that and the Coaſt of <hi>Coromandell,</hi> which reaches near, if not fully to the <hi>Cape</hi> of <hi>Comoris.</hi> For this Perſon having had much Converſation with the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43313:33"/>Divers for Pearls, not only learn'd from them, that they found the water very ſenſibly Cold at the bottom which in ſome places he eſtimated to be 80 or 100 fathom deep; but obſervd divers of them at their return to the Boats, to be ready to ſhake with Cold, and haſten to the fires that were kept ready for them in little Cabines upon the ſhore: Which Relation being accompanied with divers Circumſtances of credibility and arguing the perſon that made it to have been acquainted with the report above mentioned, and had met with ſome that had dived in the place whereto it had relation, made me conclude that as to that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port hither ſomething extraordinary had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in that place, or that there was ſome miſtake of him to whom 'twas made, or that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers did not deſcend to a ſufficiently conſiderable Depth</p>
               <p>If I had been furniſhed with opportunity, I would have engaged ſome ingenious Navigators to examine the Temperature of the Submarine-Regions, both of differing ſeaſons of the year (eſpecially the hotteſt part of <hi>Summer</hi> and Coldneſs of <hi>Winter,</hi> &amp; with Hermetically ſeal'd Weatherglaſſes in order to the Diſcovery of ſuch Particulars as theſe, <hi>Whether</hi> there be in ſome Seas any ſuch varying Differences of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature, as may invite us at leaſt in ſome places, to make more then two Submarine Regions. Whether the Submarine Coldneſſe do at the bottom of the Sea, or elſewhere either Equall or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43313:34"/>ſurpaſſe that degree which we here find ſufficient to freez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> common water. <hi>Whether</hi> the parts of the Sea-water are ſtill the Colder, as they are the deeper, And <hi>Whether</hi> or no this increaſe of Coldneſſe be regular enough to be reducible to any ſettled proportion. But for the reſolving of theſe and the like Queſtions, I did not cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſely intimate that a ſealed Weather-glaſs was to be employed; for I take a common one to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unfit for ſuch purpoſes, not only becauſe the Sea-water would mingle with ſuch Liquors as are wont to be employed in it, for that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniency I could eaſily remedy, by ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting, as I have ſeverall times don in other caſes, <hi>Mercury</hi> inſtead of ordinary Liquors: but cheifely becauſe the incumbent Sea-water would gravitate upon the reſtagnant Liquor of the Weatherglaſs, and thereby render its Informations falſe or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain. According to what I have had occaſion to obſerve in another Tract.</p>
               <p>Whereto, that there may not in this place be any need to recur, I ſhall add a ſlight experiment that I made for the ſatisfaction of ſome Ingenious men not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll acquainted with <hi>Hydroſtaticks,</hi> or not rightly principled <hi>in them.</hi> And this Tryall I ſhall the rather mention, becauſe many will not allow Water to preſs upon <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cury</hi> immersd therein, <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> being a far more ponderous Liquor then that; and others will expect, that the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Air, having no place to eſcape out at, ſhould reſiſt the aſcenſion of the ſubjacent Mercury, more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43313:34"/>than indeed it will. We made then a ſmall Weather-glaſſe differing from common ones, (beſides the bigneſſe,) in that it was turniſhed with <hi>Mercury</hi> inſtead of <hi>Water;</hi> and in that we em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to contain the ſtagnant Mercury, a Glaſs Viall with a narrow neck, wherein (by a piece of Cork or two) the Stem of the Glaſs ball was well faſtened that this globula put of the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might not be lifted up when it was under water. Then having by applying cold water to the outſide of the Ball endeavoured to reduce the Air to the ſame Temper with the Water, or at leaſt to an approaching degree of Coldneſſe; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken notice of the Station of the Mercury in the ſhanck or ſtem above mentioned; we did, (by ſtrings tyed about the neck of the ſmall Vial) let the Inſtrument gently down into a large tall glas Body filled with fair water that the Liquor and Veſſell being both tranſparent, we might eaſily perceive the motions of the Mercury in the ſlender pipe. By which means it appeared, that as the <hi>Thermometer</hi> deſcended deeper and deeper into the Water, the Mercury was preſſed up higher and higher in the Stem. And that it may not be ſuſpected, that this aſcenſion proceeded only, or cheifely, from the refrigeration of the Air by the Water, I ſhall add to what I have juſt now noted, that though the Coldneſſe of the VVater may well be ſuppoſed uniform as at leaſt to ſenſe; yet the whole inſtrument being leaſurely removed ſometimes to the upper ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43313:35"/>of the VVater. (The like Experiment we might have tryed with a <hi>Thermoſcope</hi> furniſhed with VVater and let into Oyl; or with deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quated Salt of Tartar and pure Spirit of VVine inſtead of Mercury and Water: if we had been furniſhed with ſufficient quantities of thoſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors and had judged it to be requiſite.) But this Circumſtance, I thought fit to admoniſh the ſpectators of, that tis not to be expected, that the Mercury ſhould riſe as much in proportion when it is (for example) a foot under water, as when it is but two or three Inches; becauſe according as the Inſtrument is let down deeper and the Air crowded into a leſs room, the Spring of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Air becomes the ſtronger and makes the more reſiſtance. VVhich Advertiſement agreed well with the Experiment, whoſe other <hi>Phaeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> I pas over as not pertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to this place, where <hi>I</hi> would only juſtifie what I ſaid of the unfitneſſe of Weather-glaſſes made (though with other Liquors) after the Common waies for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Submarine Tryalls I propoſed.</p>
               <p>But till ſuch Artificiall Obſervations can be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind we may from what has been above delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, probably gather that though the lowermoſt of the Submarine Regions be very ſenſibly Cold, yet VVater, at leaſt that of the Sea, does not by theſe <hi>Phaenomena</hi> appear to be the <hi>Summum Frigidum.</hi> Though <hi>I</hi> have been ſeverall times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to produce Ice in Saltwater, yet <hi>I</hi> find not by any Obſervation, that there has been Ice met with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43313:35"/>and generated at the bottom of the Sea, under which the Earth has been found unfrozen by our Divers; and appears to be ſoft at depths excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſurpaſſing the greateſt they have reacht; as is evident by the Mudd, Gravell, &amp;c. fetch'd from the bottom of the Sea by ſounding plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, let down to 80 or 100 fathom, or even a depth, whereof examples may be met with in the Journalls of Navigators; n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, my curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity procur'd me this account, from the ſober Commander of a ſhip, that came this year from the remoter parts of the great Ocean, that at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 35 degrees of Southern Latitude, the tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low with which his ſounding Lead was annointed brought him up gray Sand from the immenſe depth of no leſs then two hundred &amp; twenty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom. But to this Obſervation tis juſt to annex this Caution, That we cannot ſafely conclude from mens finding no Ice at the bottom of the Sea, that the Cold there cannot be very intenſe; for as I have found by more then one Relation (
<note n="*" place="margin">Notes aboat the Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Sea.</note> elſewhere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited) that, whatever the Schools ſurmiſe, the Sea is at leaſt as Salt at the bottom, as at the top: ſo I have more then once tryed, that Salt water will without freezing ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a much greater degree of Cold, then is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to turn freſh Water into Ice.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43313:36"/>
            <head>RELATIONS About the BOTTOM OF THE SEA.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:43313:37"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43313:37"/>
               <head>RELATIONS <hi>about the</hi> Bottom of the Sea.</head>
               <head>The Firſt SECTION.</head>
               <p>I Do not pretend to have viſited the Bottom of the Sea, but ſince none of the Naturaliſts whoſe writings I have yet met with, have been there any more then I, and 'tis great rarity in theſe cold parts of <hi>Europe</hi> to meet with any men at all that have had at once the Boldneſſe, the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, the Opportunity and the Skill to penetrate into thoſe conceal'd and dangerous Receſſes of Nature, much leſs to make any ſtay there, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it will not be unpleaſant, if about a ſubject, of which, though none of thoſe very few Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts that write any thing at all, write otherwiſe then by hear-ſay, I recite in this place, what I have learn'd by Enquity from thoſe Perſons that among the many Navigators and Travellors I have had opportunity to converſe with, were the likelieſt to give me good Information about theſe Matters.</p>
               <p>It would be needleſs here to take notice, that the Sea is uſually Cold and Salt at the bottom, nor to repeat thoſe other Things that I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43313:38"/>delivered in other Diſcourſes. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore begin what I have to ſay in this, by relating that one of the chief things that I was ſolicitous to enquire after about the Bottom of the Sea, was, the inequality I ſuppoſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Soil. For though the ſurface of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sea when 'tis not agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by the winds, appears very plain and levell, and though it be indeed, at leaſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this or that particular Sea, Sphaericall and (Phyſically ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) concentricall to the earth; yet I could not think it probable, for Reaſons not neceſſary to be here diſcourſed of, that the Bottom, the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of the Ground, or of the Veſſ ll that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it, ſhould be either flat or levell, or regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly concave.</p>
               <p>To ſatisfy my ſelfe about this matter, I enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a Perſon that had viſited the famous Pearl fiſhing at the little Iſland of <hi>Manar</hi> (near the rich Iſle of <hi>Ceylon</hi>) in the Eaſt Indies, and had by his ſtay there much opportunity to ſee Divers at their Work and converſe with them. By the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers of this man who was a Scholler, I learnt, that the Divers had aſſured him, That they found the Floor of the Sea, if I may ſo call it, in divers places exceedingly unequall, in ſome places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flat, in others aſperated with crabby Rocks a conſiderable height, and elſewhere ſinking into precipitous depths in which they found it very cold.</p>
               <p>Beſides the recited Teſtimonies of the Divers, I enquired of ſeverall Pilates and other Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43313:38"/>that had made long Voyages, what gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or abrupt inequality they had obſerv'd at their Soundings in very neighbouring places; it being eaſy to be gat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered from thence, whether the Sea were there uniformly deep, or did at leaſt with ſome regularity alter its depth by degrees, or whether as I ſuſpected, there were not at the bottom of the Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>illy places, and ſteep Praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pices, and perhaps deep Vallies or Wells, as we obſerve in the diſcovered part of the Terreſtriall Globe.</p>
               <p>By theſe inquiries I obtained ſeverall Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whereof the moſt materiall are thoſe that follow.</p>
               <p>Firſt, An ancient Sea-Commander, that had many years frequented Africa and the Indies, told me as others had don before, that when they ſail'd in the Ocean very far from ſight of Land, they did not often put themſelves to the trouble of Sounding, but that as far as they had Sounded, he had uſually found the depth of the Sea, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or decreaſe gradually, without very great irregularities, excepting ſome places, inſtancing particularly in the Excavation that makes the Bottom of the Sea, within ſight of the <hi>Cape of good Hope,</hi> where though for the moſt part, he found the water to deepen more and more as he ſailed farther from the ſhore, yet in one place, he and others had met with a Bank (as he conceived it to be) at a conſiderable diſtance from the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Water. So that though when they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43313:39"/>were as they imagined near the edge of that bank, they found but a moderate number of fathoms, yet when ſailing a very little way farther, they had gone beyond it, they found the Sea of an immenſe depth. In ſhort, I gathered from his Anſwers, that in the greater Seas, he had found for the moſt part, the ground at the bottom, to fall away by degrees; but nearer the ſhores, that is, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a moderate number of Leagues, he obſerved in divers places that the Submarine Ground was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unequall, and had as it were, Hills and Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipices.</p>
               <p>A man of Letters, that had ſailed both to the Eaſt and Weſt Indies, and in divers other Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons beſides, and had made ſome of his Voyages in ſhips of ſuch great burden, as obliged the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners to be very frequent and carefull in ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, informed me, that ſome times at conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſtances from ſhore, he had obſerved the Sea to be 20, 30, or perhaps 40 fathom deeper when they caſt the ſounding Lead from one ſide of the ſhip, then it had been juſt before, when they had ſounded from the other, and from other Things that he told me, I found my ſelf much confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the above propoſed Opinion.</p>
               <p>Hearing of a Sea-Captain of extraordinary skill in Maritine Affairs, that was come home this year from Eaſt-India, his reputation made me endeavour to have a little conference with him, about the ſubject of this diſcourſe; but his occaſions haſtening him to another place before
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43313:39"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> could ſend to him, <hi>I</hi> procur'd from the chief Perſons that employ'd him, a ſight of ſome Notes, touching his laſt Voyage, which he had left with them; hoping to ſind there ſomething at leaſt, about the Soundings of ſo accurate a Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and accordingly I met with a Paſſage, very pertinent to my purpoſe, and worthy to be here tranſcribed.</p>
               <p>Febr. 12. After our Obſervation, (he means a former one very agreeable to this) ſeeing the ground under us, we heav'd the Lead, and had but 19 fathom rocky ground, then hal'd by N.N. E<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. the Wind at N.W. and found our water to ſhoale from 19 to 10 and 8 Fathom hard Corall Ground, then ſuddainly deepned again from 8 to 20 and 22 fathom Sandy Ground, and then ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly ſaw Rocks under us, where we had but 7 fathom, and the next caſt 14 fathom again. And ſo having run N. N. E<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. from 6 in the morning till 12 at noon about 19 mile, we deepen'd our VVater, from 16 to 25, and the next caſt, no ground with 35 fathom of Line.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, having opportunely met with an Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Navigator, who paſſes for the moſt experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Pilate in our Nation for an Eaſt Indian voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; <hi>I</hi> asked him about his own Obſervations concerning theſe unequall Soundings, <hi>I</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, that he had not only met with them elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, but that not far from the mouth of out Channell, he had ſometimes found the bottom of the Sea ſo abrupt, that in ſailing twice the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43313:40"/>Length of the ſhip, he had found the VVater deepen from 30 fathom to a hundred, if not alſo much more.</p>
               <p>Since I received theſe Relations, having the honour to diſcourſe with a Noble Perſon, who has divers times deſervedly had the command of Engliſh Fleets, and is no leſs curious then intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in Maritine affairs, I took the opportunity to inquire of his Lordſhip, whether he had not obſerv'd the bottom of the Sea to be very unequal in neighbouring places? To which he reply'd, that he had found it exceedingly ſo. And to ſatisfy me that he ſpoke not upon meer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>jecture, he told me that ſailing once with his Fleet even in our Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, he perceived the VVater to make a rippling noiſe (as the Sea-men call it) as the Thames does under London Bridge. So that he was afraid they were falling upon ſome ſhoale, the VVater being 12 or 14 fathom deep, and going on a little farther, he caſt out the Plummet again, and found it about 30 fathom. He added that he made di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſuch Obſervations, but took notice of ſuch rippling VVaters only when the Tide was ebbing: and yet in a deep Sea meeting with the like ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in the upper part of the water, and thinking it improbable that there ſhould be any ſhoale there, he ordered the depth to be ſounded, and found it to exceed 30 fathoms; and after he had paſſed on a very little farther, he found the Sea ſo deep, that he could not fathom it with his ordinary Line.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43313:40"/>
               <head>The Second SECTION.</head>
               <p>ANother thing obſerv'd at the Bottom of the Sea, is the great preſſure of the water there againſt other Bodies. For what ever men may Philoſophize in their ſtudies, and may conclude from the Principles that are generally received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Non-gravitation</hi> of Water in its proper place, yet experience ſeems very little to favour that Generall Doctrine.</p>
               <p>For firſt, I remember that having caus'd a pretty large Cylinder of Glaſs, that was open only at one end, to be ſo depreſs'd into a large Glaſs veſſell full of water with a conveniently applyed weight of Lead, that none of the air could get out, I could eaſily diſcern through the Liquor and Veſſells, which were all tranſparent, that as the inverted Cylinder deſcended deeper and deeper, the externall Water compreſs'd the impriſon'd air, and aſcended higher and higher in the Cavity of the Cylinder, againſt whoſe ſide we had before hand plac'd a row of Marks, whereby to take notice of the graduall aſcent and deſcent of the Internall Water.</p>
               <p>Secondly having inquired of two ſeverall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Perſons, whereof one had with a Diving Engin viſited the bottom of the Sea in a Cold Northern Region; and the other had done the like in an Engin much of the ſame ſort, upon the coaſt of Africk, I found their Relations to agree
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43313:41"/>in this, that the deeper they deſcended into the Sea, the more the air they carried down with them was compaſſed, and the higher the Water aſcended above the Lip, or Brim of the Engin into the Cavity of it.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall now add a more conſiderable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment or two, to the ſame purpoſe. For diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing one day with an Engineer of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, that had been often at Sea, and loved to try Concluſions, of a way I had thought of, to make ſome eſtimate of the preſſure of the water at a conſiderable depth beneath the ſurface, and ſhew that the preſſure is great there, he told me he could ſave me the labour of ſome Tryalls, by thoſe he had made already, and aſſured me that having divers times opportunity to ſail near the Straights Mouth, over a place where the Sea was obſerved to be of a notable depth, he had found, that if he had let down with a weight into the Sea, not a ſtrong round Glaſs-bottle, but a Violl, ſuch as the Seamen uſe to carry their Brandy and ſtrong waters in, ſuch a Veſſell which might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Pint or a Quart of water, would when it came to be ſunk 40 fathom under water, if not ſooner, be ſo oppreſs'd, by the Preſſure of the incumbent, and laterall Water, as to be thereby broken to pieces.</p>
               <p>He alſo averred to me, that having exactly cloſed an <hi>Aeolipille</hi> of Metall, and with a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent weight, ſunk it to a great depth in the Sea, as to forty, fifty, or ſixty fathom deep, when he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43313:41"/>pull'd it up again, he found to his wonder, that the great preſſure of the water, had in divers places cruſht it inwards. And though I had ſome ſuſpition, that the coldneſs of the Sea at ſuch a depth, might by weakning the ſpring of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded Air, ſomething contribute to the effect, yet I did not admire the event, having divers years before had a thin <hi>Aeolipile</hi> of Copper cruſht inwards by the preſſure of a much lighter Fluid then Sea-water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43313:42"/>
               <head>The Third SECTION.</head>
               <p>ANother thing obſerved in the Bottom of the Sea is, the Tranquillity of the VVater there, if it be conſiderably diſtant from the ſurface. For though the VVinds have power to produce vaſt waves in that upper part of the Sea that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to their violence, yet the vehement agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diminiſhes by degrees, as the Parts of the Sea, by being deeper and deeper, lye more and more remote from the ſuperficies of the water. So that the Calm being leſs and leſs diſturb'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Bottom of the water, if that lye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably deep, the water is there either calm, or ſcarce ſenſibly diſturb'd.</p>
               <p>But that is for the moſt part to be underſtood, of places at ſome diſtance from the ſhore; for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes in thoſe that are too near it, the progreſs of the waters being rudely checkt, and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances concurring, the Commotion of the water is ſo great, that it reaches to the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, as may appear by the heaps of Sand, the Amber, and in ſome places, the ſtones that are wont to be thrown up by the Sea, in, and after ſtormes.</p>
               <p>The above mentioned Calmneſs of the Sea at the Bottom (will I doubt not) appear ſtrange to many, who admiring the force of ſtormy Winds, and the vaſtneſs of the VVaves they raiſe, do not at the ſame time, conſider the almoſt incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43313:42"/>greater Quantity, and weight of VVater that muſt be mov'd, to make any great commotion at the bottom of the Sea, upon which ſo great a Maſs of Salt-water, which is heavier then freſh, is conſtantly incumbent. VVherefore for the Proof of the propos'd Paradox, I will here ſet down a memorable Relation, which my inquiries got me from the Diver elſewhere mentioned, who by the help of an Engin could ſtay ſome hours under VVater.</p>
               <p>This Perſon then being ask'd, whether he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved any operation of the VVinds at the bottom of the Sea, where it was of any conſiderable depth? Anſwered me to this purpoſe, That the VVind being ſtiffe, ſo that the waves were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſix or ſeven foot high above the ſurface of the VVater, he found no ſigne of it at 15 fathom deep; but if the Blaſts continued long, then it mov'd the Mudd at the Bottom, and made the water thick and dark. And I remember he told me, which was the Circumſtance I chiefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, that ſtaying once at the bottom of the Sea very long, where it was conſiderably deep, he was amaz'd at his return to the upper parts of the water, to find a Storm there which he dreamt not of, and which was raiſed in his abſence, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken no notice of it below, and having left the Sea calm enough when he deſcended into it.</p>
               <p>For farther Confirmation, I ſhall add, that having inquired of a great Traveller, who had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted at a rich Pearl-fiſhing in Eaſt Indies, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43313:43"/>he had not learnt by his Converſation with the Divers, that ſtorms reach not to the bottom of the Sea, if it be of any conſiderable depth, he anſwer'd, that he had ſeen the Divers take the Water, when the Sea was ſo very rough, that ſcarce any Veſſells, would hazard themſelves out of Ports, that thoſe returning Divers told him, that at the Bottom, they had found no diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the Water at all. Which is the more conſiderable, becauſe of the ſcituation of that place where they dive for Pearls; for this is near the ſhore of <hi>Manar,</hi> and that it ſelf is ſealed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the great Iland of <hi>Ceylon,</hi> and the vaſt Cape of <hi>Comori:</hi> and though it may be much nearer the former, is not yet far diſtant from the latter. Which ſcituation and the Neighbourhood of the vaſt Indian Ocean, on the one ſide of <hi>Ceylon,</hi> and the great Gulfe of <hi>Bengala,</hi> (antiently <hi>Sinus Gangeticus</hi>) on the other, makes the place where the Pearls are fiſhed for, exceeding likely to be ſubject to very troubled Seas.</p>
               <p>It will perhaps be thought no ſlight addition to the fore-going Arguments, if I here add, that meeting one day with an ancient and expert Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whom his merit had advanc'd to conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Employments in his Profeſſion, I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the Inquiries I made of him, not only in the Opinion I had about the Calmneſs of the Bottom of the Sea, but alſo that the operation of good Gales of VVind, does oftentimes not reach to near ſo conſiderable depths into the Sea,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43313:43"/>as hath been hitherto ſuppoſed, even by Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors themſelves. For he aſſured mee, that having ſometimes ſailed in great Ships that drew much water, as about 12 or 15 foot, he had Div'd to the Keel of the ſhipps, when they are under Sail, and obſerv'd the Agitations of the Water, to be exceedingly diminiſh'd, and grown very languid, even at that ſmall diſtance, from the upper part of the Waves. And he farther anſwered, that when in <hi>America</hi> he learned to Dive of the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they taught him by their Examples, to creep along by the Rocks and great ſtones, that lay near the ſhore at the Bottom of the Water, to ſhelter themſelves from the ſtrokes, and other ill effects of the Billows, which near the ſhore, and where the Sea was ſo ſhallow, as it was there, did often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurt and endanger Swimmers and unskillfull Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. But when they were by this means got fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Shore and into deeper VVater, they would ſecurely leave the ſhelter they had till then made uſe of, and ſwim within a few yards of the Surface of the Sea, as fearing there no danger from the To ſings and Commotions of the upper parts of the Water.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, for further ſatisfaction, I had the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to make inquiry about this matter of a great Sea Commander who has both an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary curioſity to make marine Obſervations, &amp; an unuſuall Care in making of them accurate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I found the Opinion countenanced by his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, which was in ſhort; That he had lately
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43313:44"/>been at a place where the Sea was often tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous enough, and that they found by a ſure mark that the Storm did not reach with any efficacy four fathom beneath the Surface of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>About the Tranquillity of the Lower Parts of very deep waters I had a ſuſpition, which though I fear it might ſeem ſomewhat extravagant, becauſe I have not met with it in Authors; yet I thought it worth examining for the uſe it might be of, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd in reference to the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea.</p>
               <p>I made therefore a Solicitous Inquiry whether the Tides did reach to, or near the Bottom of the deeper Seas, but found it exceeding difficult by reaſon of mens want of Curioſity to obtain any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisſaction about a Problem that moſt Navigators I have converſed with did not ſeem to have ſo much as dreamd of. But thus much I found in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by inquiring of an Engineer who was curious of Marine Obſervations, that a famous Sea Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of his Acquaintance being alſo a great Mathematician, had affirmed to this Relator, that he had divers times obſerv'd, that when he let down his Plummer to a great depth but yet not to reach ground, it would be quickly carried by a motion quite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to that of the Shallop whence they ſounded and very much qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cker then it; but I had this only at ſecond hand. Alſo, if I mis-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not, I was informed by a skillfull Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver that commanded many of our Engliſh men
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43313:44"/>of Warr, that he had near the ſound obſerved the upper and Lower parts of the VVater to move with a conſiderable ſwiftneſs quite different wais; but not having committed this Relation to wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I dare not build much upon it. And among the Anſwers I had received and written down con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe matters, all that I can yet find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong my Adverſaria, is a Relation which though ſingle, will not be unworthy to be tranſcrib'd in this Place, becauſe the Perſon who gave it me, is one of the ancientſt and moſt experien'ſt Pilots of our Nation.</p>
               <p>This Perſon therefore aſſured me, that ſayling beyond the <hi>Cape of Good Hope</hi> into the South Seas, made Tryalls of the motion of the upper part of the Water above the lower, where ſometimes caſting out a large and heavy Plummet, he let it down to ſeverall depths ſhort of 50 fathom, without any ſenſible Operation upon the motion of the Boat, or Shallop he ſtood in to make the Tryall; but when he let down the Plummet lower, to about an hundred fathom or more, then he found that though the Plummet reached not to the Bottom of the Water, yet upon the ſcore of the ſtanding water beneath, the Superior VVater would make the Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t turn towards the Tide or Current, as if it lay at Anchor, and the water would run by the ſide of the Boat at the rate of about three mile an hour, Thus far this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Obſerver. But how far the inequality of the Soil at the bottom of the Sea, and how far the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43313:45"/>various depth of the VVater, and ſome other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, may alter the caſe, and make it hard to determine, what ought to be aſcribed to Tides and what to Currents, and are things which I will by no means be poſitive in; till I can meet with further Information.</p>
               <p>[Since the writing of this, hapning to meet with one that ſpent ſome time at a famous Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Pearle-fiſhing, and asked him whether he had inquired of the Divers about the Problem lately propoſed, and whether the Sea were there deep enough to make obſervations of that kind: To the latter part of which Queſtion he replyed, that in ſome places it was of a very conſiderable depth, and fit to make the obſervation in; And to the former he anſwered, That he had inquired of the Divers, who affirmed to him that ſometimes at the Bottom of the Deep waters there ſeem'd to be a ſtagnation of the Sea for a great depth, ſo that till ſuch a height they could riſe directly upwards, but that at other heights they would be carried away by the leſſe deep-waters; ſo as to be found when they came to emerge a great way off from that point of the ſurface which was perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to that place at the Bottom, whence they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to aſcend.]</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:43313:45"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
